

# PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- -SQL (MySQL, PostgreSQL)
- -Python (NumPy, Pandas, Scikitlearn, Keras)
- -Microsoft
- -Latex
- -MATLAB
- -Git
- -R
- -AWS Athena(SQL)
- -Java
- -Power BI
- -Tableau
- -C, C++ and C#

### **PERSONAL SKILLS**

- -Ability to analyze complex technical information
- -Reliable and professional
- -Detail orientation
- -Time management
- -Team player
- -Fast learner
- -Motivated

### WEBSITE

• https://aovaldes2.github.io/Alejandro-O-Valdes-

Portfolio/index.html

## CONTACT



- +34 631 327 628
- linkedin.com/in/aovaldes2



aovaldes2@gmail.com



Leganés, Madrid

### LANGUAGES

- Native: Spanish
- Fluent: English

# ALEJANDRO O. VALDÉS

### DATA SCIENTIST

### **ABOUT**

Data Scientist graduated in mathematics with multiple postgraduate studies and experience in education and as a data analyst. With a team-oriented attitude, I am always eager to contribute with my abilities in programming and applied mathematics.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

**DATA SCIENTIST** 

Freelance | Nov 2021 - Present

- Development of an ensemble model (XGBoost, Catboost, and Random Forest) algorithm to predict the probability of employee retention.
- Implementation of tabular models using Analysis Services with Power BI.
  Creation of intuitive Power BI dashboards for evaluating performance and efficiency in personnel management.

PRIVATE TEACHER (MATH, PROGRAMMING)

Academia | Sept 2020 - Jul 2022

DATA ANALYST (TRAINEESHIP)

Openbank | Mar 2020 - Aug 2020

- -Migration project:
- Analysis of controls generated for migration.
- Resolution of incidents obtained in the data cleansing process.
- Creation of Excel reports, dashboards and performing data validation activities
- -Business Analytics for T&O:
- Implemented ETL processes from various sources to QuickSight using AWS Athena (SQL).
- Created different types of dashboards in Amazon QuickSight, including static, interactive, analytical, and temporal.

### MATH TEACHER

University of Havana| Sept 2016 - Mar 2017

• Teaching Mathematics I in the degree of Food Sciences.

Technological University of Havana | Aug 2014 - Aug 2016

 Teaching multiple engineering courses, including Mathematics I, II, and IV and Numerical Mathematics.

### **EDUCATION**

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE, MATHEMATICS

University of Havana | 2010 - 2014 GPA 9.2

MASTER OF SCIENCE, MATHEMATICAL ENGINEERING

University Carlos III of Madrid | 2018 - 2020

BOOTCAMP DATA SCIENCE

The Bridge Digital Talent Accelerator | 2021



### **APTITUDES TÉCNICAS**

- -SQL (MySQL, PostgreSQL)
- -Python (NumPy, Pandas, Scikitlearn, Keras)
- -Microsoft
- -l atex
- -MATLAB
- -Git
- -R
- -AWS Athena(SQL)
- -Java
- -Power BI
- -Tableau
- -C, C++ and C#

# APTITUDES PERSONALES

- -Capacidad para analizar información técnica compleja
- -Confiable y profesional
- -Orientación al detalle
- -Gestión del tiempo
- -Trabajo en equipo
- -Facilidad para el aprendizaje

### WEBSITE

• https://aovaldes2.github.io/Alejandro-O-Valdes-

Portfolio/index.html

## CONTACTO



- linkedin.com/in/aovaldes2
- ac
- aovaldes2@gmail.com



• Leganés, Madrid

### **IDIOMAS**

- Nativo: Español
- Fluido: Inglés

# ALEJANDRO O. VALDÉS

### DATA SCIENTIST

### **PERFIL**

Data Scientist graduado en matemáticas con múltiples estudios de postgrado y experiencia en el sector educativo y como analista de datos. Orientado al trabajo en equipo y siempre estoy dispuesto a contribuir con mis habilidades en la programación y las matemáticas aplicadas.

### **EXPERIENCIA LABORAL**

DATA SCIENTIST

Freelance | Nov 2021 - Present

- Desarrollo de un algoritmo de modelo ensamblado (XGBoost, Catboost y Random Forest) para predecir la probabilidad de retención de empleados.
- Implementación de modelos tabulares utilizando Analysis Services con Power Bl. Creación de tableros intuitivos de Power Bl para evaluar el desempeño y la eficiencia en la gestión del personal.

PROFESOR PARTICULAR (MATEMÁTICAS, PROGRAMACIÓN) Academia | Sept 2020 - Jul 2022

DATA ANALYST (TRAINEESHIP)

Openbank | Mar 2020 - Aug 2020

- -Proyecto de migración:
- Análisis de controles generados para la migración.
- Resolución de incidencias obtenidas en el proceso de limpieza de datos.
- Creación de informes en Excel, dashboards y realizando actividades de validación de datos.
- -Business Analytics para T&O:
- Implementar procesos ETL desde varias fuentes a QuickSight utilizando AWS Athena (SQL).
- Crear diferentes tipos de dasboards en Amazon QuickSight, incluyendo estáticos, interactivos, analíticos y temporales.

### PROFESOR UNIVERSITARIO DE MATEMÁTICAS

Universidad de la Habana| Sept 2016 - Mar 2017

• Enseñar Matemática I en el grado de Ciencias de la Alimentación.

Technological University of Havana | Aug 2014 - Aug 2016

• Enseñar en múltiples cursos de ingeniería, incluidos Matemáticas I, II, and IV and Matemática Numérica.

### HISTORIAL ACADÉMICO

LICENCIATURA EN MATEMÁTICAS

Universidad de la Habana | 2010 - 2014 N.G: 9.2

MASTER EN INGENIERÍA MATEMÁTICA

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid | 2018 - 2020

BOOTCAMP DATA SCIENCE

The Bridge Digital Talent Accelerator | 2021